"Taurine Supplementation Increases Lifespan
and Healthspan in Animals"
The level of taurine
in the bodies
of mice, monkeys,
and men, and women,
declines with age,
dropping by nearly 80 percent
over the lifespan.
This is due, in rats at least,
to a decline
in the synthesis of taurine.
Would there be any benefit
to restoring youthful levels
through taurine supplementation?
After all,
lower taurine levels
have been associated
with all sorts
of disease conditions
of the bone, blood,
eyes, heart, cancer.
Of course, just because
there's a correlation
between lower levels and disease
doesn't necessarily mean that
lower levels cause disease.
It could be
the other way around,
where, for example, disease
leads to lower taurine levels.
In my last video,
I talked about how taurine
is an antioxidant
in the context of inflammation.
So, in the context of disease,
more taurine
may just get used up.
The only way to know
if taurine may help
is to put it to the test.
We know blood concentrations
of taurine declines with age.
So, to investigate
whether this decline
contributes to aging,
researchers fed taurine,
or not,
to middle-aged mice
until the end of their life.
And taurine-fed mice
lived longer,
significantly longer,
like, the human equivalent
of seven to eight years longer.
And they had only
started the taurine
later in life,
in middle-age.
Now, a meaningful
anti-aging therapy
should not only improve
lifespan but also healthspan,
the period of healthy living.
So, researchers
then investigated
the health of the
taurine-fed middle-aged mice
and found,
compared to the control group,
improved functioning of bone,
muscle, pancreas, brain, fat,
gut, and immune system,
indicating an overall increase
in healthspan
as well as lifespan.
They also tried it
on other species.
Taurine didn't
make yeast live longer,
but it did increase
the lifespan
of microscopic worms.
Ten percent or more
increased average lifespan
in middled-aged worms and mice,
and the mice
didn't just live longer
but also healthier,
with improvements
in strength,
coordination, and memory,
as well as attenuation
of multiple hallmarks of aging
such as cellular senescence,
DNA damage,
and chronic inflammation,
many of the aging pathways
I talked about
in my longevity book,
How Not to Age.
And in middle-aged
rhesus macaque monkeys,
six months
of taurine supplementation
led to positive effects
on bone health, metabolism,
and apparent immune health.
There were similar
health effects in monkeys
who were the middle-age
equivalent of a human
about 45 to 50 years old,
but that's still
15 years for a monkey,
which is why it's so hard
to do longevity experiments
on monkeys.
If you're a microscopic worm,
"middle-age" is just two weeks,
so, it's a lot easier.
But, researchers did find
that even just six months
of extra taurine
had beneficial effects
on most tested health parameters
in middle-aged monkeys,
including one or two
fewer pounds (450 or 900 g)
of weight gain,
better bone mineral density,
better blood sugars,
and lower measures
of inflammation and oxidation.
If you take people,
and have them exercise,
at least in active individuals,
exercise increases
the concentration
of taurine in the blood.
So, that might even
partially explain
the anti-aging
effects of exercise.
The bottom line is that
taurine supplementation
makes animals live longer,
but what that means
for people is unclear.
This is not the first time
benefits
of taurine supplementation
have been demonstrated
in lab animals,
reducing blood pressure in rats
or reducing atherosclerosis
in the coronary arteries
of rabbits fed cholesterol.
But the extrapolation
of findings
from animal studies
is difficult,
due to problems
not only with dosing
but the biological
differences between species.
For example, the final step
in taurine synthesis
in rodents
involves a completely
different enzyme
than in people,
and is actually
much more efficient
in them than in us.
But maybe it needs
to be so much more efficient
because the normal levels
in the blood
and brains of rodents
may be as much
as ten times higher,
potentially making them
more susceptible
to problems with
slipping levels as they age.
Unfortunately, little
is known about the effects
of taurine
supplementation in humans.
Here's a graphical
illustration of the study.
Taurine levels
decrease with age,
and taurine supplementation
to reverse this trend
can increase
the lifespan of animals
by countering
the many drivers of aging
and boosting health
in the process.
In people,
lower taurine levels
correlate with worse health,
but the missing piece,
a randomized clinical trial
of taurine in people.
What should we do while we wait?
Correction of late-life
taurine decline in humans
could be beneficial
for cognitive performance,
energy metabolism,
sexual function, and vision,
but clinical studies
remain to be performed.
There have been some short-term
randomized controlled trials
of taurine supplementation
in people.
And I'll run through
what they found, next.